Finding Aid for Dept. of Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering (University of Michigan) publications, 1964-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering (University of Michigan) publications 1964-1992, 1984-1992
University of Michigan. Dept. of Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering.
0.5 linear feet
9723; Bimu; C146; 2
Department in the University of Michigan College of Engineering. Publications includes bibliographies, brochures and pamphlets, bulletins such as Research in Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering, histories including Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering at the University of Michigan, 1881-1981, lectures, and manuals such as the Literate Naval Architect. Also includes newsletters such as the Nautilus and The Naval Architecture Log. Also includes student publications such as the newsletter The Deadweight from the Quarterdeck Society.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The publications are received periodically from the unit (donor no. 5457 ) and Professor Harry Benford (donor no. 3123 ). 5457
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The publications are open for research.
The first courses in ship design was offered in 1881 by Mortimer Cooley, assistant engineer in the U.S. navy who had been detailed to the university as professor of Steam Engineering and Iron Shipbuilding. The department was established in 1899 and in 1900 Herbert Charles Sadler was hired as Junior Professor of Architecture and Marine Engineering. The first degree was awarded in 1902. In 1904 the department took up quarters in the new Engineering Building (West Engineering) with classroom and lab facilities including the 300 foot long naval testing tank.
In addition to its instructional activities, the department has from the .beginning supported a research, design, testing and consulting activities for commercial, pleasure and military vessels. There has been a particular interest in matters relating to Great Lakes Shipping.
The Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering publications (0.5 linear feet) are divided into three series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, and Student Publications. The bulk of the publications document the teaching and research functions of the Department of Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Ocean Engineering Laboratory.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; Quarterdeck Society (University of Michigan); Quarterdeck Society (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Ocean Engineering Laboratory.; Ocean engineering laboratory participation in the Mackinac Bridge recovery, 26 September-1 October 1989.; Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering at the University of Michigan, 1881-1981.; Nautilus.; Naval architecture log.; Deadweight.
Genre Terms:
Bibliographies.; Pamphlets.; Bulletins.; Histories.; Lectures.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Reports.; Student publications.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the Department of Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication.
  The Unit Publications series includes bibliographies, brochures and pamphlets, bulletins, histories, lectures, manuals, newsletters, programs and reports. The history Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering at the University of Michigan, 1881-1981 was written to document the centennial of the department. The Literate Naval Architect was written by Professor Harry Benford, in 1965 and updated in 1967, as a tongue-in-cheek guide for NAME students as they write papers for their various courses at Michigan. Newsletters such as The Naval Architecture Log and its successor The Nautilus document the faculty, staff, students, and alumni of the Department of Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering from 1991 to the present.
  - Bibliographies
    - Department Report Series, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - General 1973-1992 (Box 1)
    - Careers in Naval Architecture*Marine Engineering, undated (Box 1)
    - Graduate Programs in Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering, 1968-1987 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - Focus on Naval Architecture, circa 1986 (Box 1)
    - Research and Education in Offshore Engineering, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Research in Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering, 1974, undated (Box 1)
  - Histories
    - Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering at the University of Michigan, 1881-1981, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Lectures
    - Of Ships and Shipping, 2000 A.D. by Harry Benford, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Manuals
    - The Literate Naval Architect, 1965, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - Der Hauptschlag Michigans, v. 1, 1970 (Box 1)
    - The Nautilus, v. 4-20 [Supersedes The Naval Architecture Log], 1993-2001, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - The Naval Architecture Log, v. 1-3 [Precedes The Nautilus], 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Programs
    - Groundbreaking 1977 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Investigation of the Sunken Schooner Barge, Newell A. Eddy in Lake Huron, Michigan, 1992 (Box 1)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications series contains publications from subordinate offices, departments, programs and organizations within the Department of Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering. These publications are arranged alphabetically by the creating sub-unit. This series contains a report from the Ocean Engineering Laboratory documenting the lab's participation in a Mackinac Bridge recovery operation of a vehicle that had gone off the bridge in 1989.
  - Ocean Engineering Laboratory
    - Reports
      - Ocean Engineering Laboratory Participation in the Mackinac Bridge Recovery, 26 September-1 October, 1989, undated (Box 1)
- Student Publications
  The Student Publications series contains publications published by student groups within the Department of Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering. In this series the researcher will find scattered issues of the newsletter The Deadweight and a humorous report entitled The Principles of Naval Architecture from the Quarterdeck Society. In 1970 Howard F. Alberty and Ernest K. Jacquet, students of the department, presented a paper to the Gulf Section of the Society of Naval Architects and Marine Engineers. A copy of that presentation is in this series.
  - Quarterdeck Society
    - Newsletters
      - The Deadweight, 1967-1992, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Reports
      - Principles of Naval Architecture, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Student Projects
    - Presentations
      - Dermadrive, Presented to the Gulf Section, The Society of Naval Architects and Marine Engineers, 1970 (Box 1)